so we we want to start with your
question on transcendence and I'm going
to allow my running need to talk about
non orden interest in non-ordinary
experiences to inform how our
conversation on transcendence how's that
sound that sounds fine I would recommend
that we set that as it I would it sounds
better to me to set that as an intention
and then stay in open space together
because when we said when we did that
last time our conversation was like
novel and buoyant and fun and yeah it
was more of a sense of co-creation than
before yeah I'm we won't have we don't
de force the direction but I'm aware of
every time now talking to you there's a
little voice in my head about I don't
even know what the question is but this
disinterest in it in it so we'll see
we'll see what's up yeah that's great ok
so my my feeling about transcendence is
that I sometimes don't know what the
word means especially when spiritual
teachers use it and I think I used to
know what the word meant or used to
think that I knew what the word meant
and in the past had experiences that
would make more sense to call
transcendent but more and more over the
last couple years especially under the
influence of waking down and mutuality
transmission and teachers I feel like
somehow trance transcendence as a
descriptor of a reality which is
conceived of as more basic or truer
perhaps even as more contextual doesn't
really make sense
and in a feeling way I fall further
towards a very paradoxical why it's
difficult but very very doc sickle
innate or not innate but like kind of in
my heart sensing of some subtle kind of
the non separateness between context and
content being so profound that context
itself is no longer highlighted as even
truer or made more basic or something
like that so I'm not I sort of the
emphasis on like on reality like a true
reality or more important to a more
valuable reality or more valuable
perspective or experience being one of
for example feeling like life and
everything is moving within something
that isn't moving and you are that thing
that isn't moving or whatever that feels
like a limit or sometimes I think of it
as a stage and then there's a beyond
that that isn't beyond because the
metaphor of transcendent isn't working
for me anymore for me it was like a
falling in we're all experiences even
absolute experiences this is how I've
been unhelpful it's all experiences have
been relativized even absolute
experiences there's only transition and
change in in the sense that they're all
originals have the same source which I
call the heart and the end and context
and content art both fused and inter
penetrative and can give windows on each
other and temporary and all this sort of
things so there's no I don't even know
what it would mean to and it's always
changing and there's always opening up
to more more everything everything is
infinite everything is infinite
including the finite and the and the
infinite is finite it's that
as well so I'm not sure what
transcendence means anymore and I'm not
sure whether emphasizing it spiritual
teachers emphasizing it is altogether as
helpful as I think it's only
instrumentally helpful utilitarian and
then utilitarian sense and not true or
absolutely helpful or something like
that so but I don't get the sense that
many people think or talk this way and
it leaves me wondering whether I'm
missing something or what this
transcendence is that spiritual teachers
are referring to yeah so I think your
intuition or you're feeling sense of
what you're talking around is real and
the one of the quotes out so that one of
the questions is you know can we create
a language or two or a framework to
better articulate what you're trying to
say so then I can start to make some
distinctions you know so that that would
be important and so we'll just I want to
just start easy and simple and then we
can try to grow this into something more
complex but you know so the first thing
I wrote down when you said that this
easy thing is this concept of when
people use the term transcendence I'm
not saying you're doing this we're going
to start just talking about the common
ways that people work with this notion
and then we'll get out to that edge
you're talking about right so that we
can figure out what we're talking about
so one of the ways people use that is in
terms they have like they're basically
setting up some kind of spatialized
metaphor right so transcendent is
farther from something and closer to
something right so people talk about
that transcend
God the Creator is farther away somehow
there's some kind of spatial metaphor
that's being enacted so if so if i have
a non-ordinary experience and somebody
says that's transcendent you know uses
that term the site transcendent
experience then the overtone in the
spatial category somehow that's closer
to God right yeah and I'm hearing you
saying that you disagree with this or
this doesn't seem to be the case or you
reject that I mean I rejected too you
know so i will say yeah i mean you could
categorize that as a transcendent
experience but it's not closer or
further to God you know there's this
disentangle this the spatial metaphor
from it now some people that is the
overtone that they're using when they
use that term a transcendent truth is
somehow closer to the real truth than a
relative truth you know so so that's one
use of the word that can create some
problematic aspects of spirituality
so the other thing that is an
experiential I think aspect of the term
transcendent transcend I'm going to keep
talking until you you formulate
something that really catches what your
question is okay I mean is the at the
ability for the self to create multiple
recursive witnesses right this is a
rather modern phenomenon modern since
Homer the you know if you read Julian
Jane's in a bicameral mind that was the
first time that there was this ability
to have a recursive personality a
self-reflection and Julian Jane's talks
about it the transitional phase when you
read homers first book The Iliad those
that viewpoint was associated with the
gods these demigods and then by the time
you get to the Odyssey that viewpoint
was recognized as a human capacity so so
his argument is right around then this
capacity have people with so you know I
mean there are people that I know that
have so many notes the hall of mirrors
you tell people get there there's so
many layers of you know and and each one
of those is considered transcendent to
the others until you get to the ultimate
witness which is spiritual eyes din the
of the of the witness that will
transcend and can see all others ok so
so that term transcendence has to do
with this ability of the
mind to create these gaps between
observer and experience right and at
let's say one level of recursion it's
relatively ordinary experience at
someone who at least went through post
modern Western education and that a
higher level experience you have people
that go through let's say psychodynamic
therapy or the spiritual traditions
where you start really getting very
recursive making object out of
everything and then the spiritual
traditions will hypothesize this
ultimate witness and different spiritual
dish traditions do different things with
that so some spiritual traditions will
talk about that as the ultimate I am
Wilbur actually talks about the witness
is the last barrier toward yep one taste
right so labor so now that's another way
of looking at that go ahead well I
haven't it that I was just thinking
about that last night I mean this
question is I'm bringing up this
question now because I was reading some
Wilbur last night and thinking of that
and watch bunch of Thomas who will this
morning interviews with him and so the
question is sparked by that and I have
clarified the reason I wanted to ask the
question was mostly just because I feel
differently but i doubt it and wanted to
know what you thought well I in a sense
that like for example if we talk about
Wilbur's thing I was reflecting that I'm
actually glad that I went through a
process of emphasizing
went through a period of stable e
emphasizing having emphasized it being
an experience of the witness because the
after that the clarity and the
perspective that came from it was still
there but for example on waking down
it's sort of a I think it's at least a
theme amongst many students certainly
not everyone that they kind of fall into
for this paradoxical mmm relative is a
shin of all experience including witness
experiences or absolute experiences are
enlightened states and stages but
without having gone through a period of
radical clarification of the object
nature of all experiences and then they
don't have that confidence and clarity
that comes from it and so again in the
sense I that still strengthens my my
argument that the wit that consciousness
that transcendent experiences of many
different flavors I really think are you
are tools they're actually just they're
just tools not ends in themselves and
that and it's an and resting one's hat
there for any reason any reason at all
is is it's more than just silly it
actually feels untrue and a little bit a
little bit immature and a little bit
also not
not it feels like a view based on that
even a realization authentic realization
can somehow miss people who are in there
all right that's hard to describe for me
but like Miss people who are living a
more paradoxical sort of non special
experience non not an ordinary
experience and yet they are at the same
time it just doesn't show up as
emphasizing the absolute for example or
doesn't show up as emphasizing the
experiences being that which all things
move through cetera so I don't really I
I would love to you know hear thoughts
and yeah what what just we're still
talking around so so what that made me
think of is it you know when you say
immature or something I think the word I
would use is there's a confusion you
know you can see people are tied or lost
in some confusion and confusion can be
disentangled by making some of the
distinctions that you're making and so
one of the confusions that I see is that
you will have people like postmodern
secularists and they will argue that
spiritual views are conditioned by
cultures and we can understand you could
relativize all these spiritual views is
conditioned by cultures but then a
religious community a spiritual
community will say that spiritual
absolutes transcend cultural
conditioning right and you can argue
this forever because both of them are
meta views right one is saying that I
you know that for example there's a
great book I can't remember it comes
from it talks about how Buddhism
in India was developed developed within
the caste system there and so the
Buddhist scholastics were born into
these monastic traditions where they
didn't work the fields they weren't
allowed to work the fields because if
you work the fields even if you were
strict vegetarian you would kill some
things by working the fields and so you
had these monks that had this certain
way of absolute izing existence and then
when this travelled into China and the
Buddhist scholastics the main teachings
gets incorporated into Chinese society
where everybody is working the fields
and the Taoist scholastics took that
then that became the foundation for Zen
and a lot of the Zen monastic process
was to do a lot of hard labor to you
know watch rotting corpses to it was
exactly opposite to get as close to you
know this this eminent relative world as
possible so that so that would be a
critique that says the spirituality
develops within the cultural context
right but when you're inside those
spiritual communities that view is a
view that says all these cultural
contexts are conditioned and this
spirituality transcends those conditions
in the problem with these metal views is
that they can each hold each other you
know that we have a concept that one has
got to be bigger or smaller than the
other when in reality we can switch in
one view can hold compute you know the
cultural view can contextualize
spirituality and spirituality can
contextualize the cultural view this you
know so so arm this seems to be the case
for all
meta views meta commentaries so it can
be frustrating because I like to tell
this story you know you live all your
life on the side of the mountain and
then you start and you think that all
reality is what you can see and you
start to climb the mountain and now you
can see where you lived and you realize
the higher you can go the more you can
see until you get to the top and when
you get to the top you just see 10,000
melons you know so there's no end to
that process either as what I'm saying
and you don't get to an absolute view so
that's what I would say with a confusion
was in terms of people who get to a med
of you or a transcendent view or can and
don't understand that what they're
looking at can also be turned around and
look and contextualize them and in many
cases there's a big food food fight
about that right so if that happened to
Wilbur's aqua theory and that he claims
it can contextualize everything and now
people are saying oh you know only a
Western developmentalist epigenetic
psychologists grown up in middle-class
America could even come up with a such a
thing so they're the this this seems to
be always the case so that relat I
devises all these men of use right in
and so that was a little bit of what you
were saying right all right really and
that's only one definition of
transcendence is
you know the witness is the experiential
version of it the med of you is the
theoretical version of it right like you
can see your view my view can see your
view so it must be higher you know like
that is interesting right right so I so
it sounds like you're agreeing I'm just
trying to make sure I just try to help
you articulate what I think you're
saying so we can move slowly into where
the question is yes so so far we're
agreeing yeah yes so so far you yeah
that's been helpful yes yeah but you
know we you know some subtle caveats
because I'm painting I'm I'm sort of
making a big I feel like I'm making a
very big claim and but it's also subtle
and hard to fairly hard to pinpoint um
so like for example I understand that
the witness consciousness is not the
only is not the only experience that I'm
lumping in the category of transcendent
experiences right now there's multiple
so we should proceed on that place yeah
we said the Wilbur that's one way they
use the word transcendent is this actual
experience of the recursively reflective
self but I mean even within the
spiritual domain different types of all
right so let's flavors of transcendent
experiences okay so we have the witness
we have the the way the actual
scholastics contextualize it we just so
what other well the three the three big
ones that I'm thinking of off the top of
my head right now are an experience of
and then they might just be different
metaphors but an experience of awareness
which yeah as an experience of awareness
which is aware of all things and then
then there's sort of an experience of
nothingness and all of these can be
stable things an experience
nothingness which isn't ever really an
experience but it's intuited in the
process of realizing that even awareness
or knowing of anything is is somehow
superseded or a very subtle very very
subtle experience that's always in
relationship to that which it's noticing
so somehow there isn't really an
experience of nothingness but but it's
sort of like paints a shadow on
everything else once it's intuited which
I actually think another direction we
might go here is whether that's
different than unconsciousness I think
it might their experience subjective
reasons why it might be different on the
way getting into their getting out of
there and and what its results are that
might be neurological differences but in
terms of just what unconsciousness means
I think it's the same it's just non
experience of any kind and then a third
is more is neither of those but it's the
sense of there's another broader
category of context being emphasized
over content and that could be
temporally or or sort of spatio
somatically and which both of which can
have relationships to the sense of
identity and who one is so space show
somatically is what I said before the
sense of like even when you move you're
not really moving it's just that things
are moving yeah in you and then
temporarily it would be like things
start and it's like you don't start and
end you can't die for example yeah there
are just things that start and end but
like within you I get account so they're
related and not drawing these
distinctions perfectly clearly but um so
that's sort of what I'm talking about
and I'm lumping all of those together
yeah yeah no that's good all right so
can we stop here cuz yeah this is it's a
lot already yeah
so first I want to say that that you
know and I'm not accusing you this
because I think this is this is not the
case with you but but but when you have
these experiences of nothingness or
these these dis products experience of
awareness that is not necessarily
conditioned let's say our content list
that they're emphasized by by the
importance of these experiences
emphasized by like the very cycle active
type experiences right so when we're not
we're going to sound like we're talking
about theory but we wanna i want to
point that that these experiences have
um the quality that comes with the
experience is extraordinary right so I'm
not talking about theory no no I know
but I just for those who are listening I
just want to say that we're only talking
about certain types of experience that
that would sound like we're talking
about it were but we're trying to point
to it something that's been experienced
so right and also quality that comes
with it is a sense of truth like it is
true that is adding more true then or
through that right it comes as a great
insight yeah right like oh my god I
can't die exactly obvious it's looking
up rights just earrings shows that it's
proof it's just is exactly that I think
it was Ramana Maharshi that said like
there's three stages at one stage you
know you don't even know there's a
diamond and at the second stage it might
have been Alamos might I said that who
knows i read too much yeah somebody else
then the second stage you know the
diamonds in your coat pocket right and
then the third stage is you can feel the
diamond in your coat pocket what you
still haven't seen it and then when you
see it it's just so
obvious right so those are stages of
inference right like like more and more
and more clarity and in the end people
will say well how do you know there's
like the witness well once you know it
it's like a it's like somebody saying
well how do you know it's raining
outside it's just it's not it's just a
given the experience comes to as just
more true than all this kind of complex
confusion that or that you've had before
so all right so that's just a side point
I think what you're talking about in
terms of the the way we know these
things now now that we've said that
there's a psychoactive component that
that there's a process of infer
inference right like so if i can see
that tree over there and see that a tree
over there and measure between them then
i must be i can infer from the trees
though like the stars when you're when
you're if you're navigating if i can let
stars over there and that stars over
there i can triangulate my position
right I can't directly know where I am
but I can infer it right and so this
process of knowing that nothingness or
knowing the awareness is a process of
inferring from what is not nothing or
from what is not awareness and so
there's a long history of teaching with
that capacity of inference you know that
we know things that didn't come by
reasoning we can infer that knowledge
comes through just embodied existence
right because I know I didn't make it up
but I know it for sure so these are
processes of inference and
that's a whole nother topic of the rich
capacity of inference and yeah and in
fact that's what the witness how you get
rid of the witness because the witness
realizes that even the witness is an
object in the consciousness of some
thing else and if that's not going to be
a more recursive witness then you can
only infer what that is is nothing that
arises as an object in your
consciousness including the witness and
that's when the witness dissolves right
so the inference cuts through this
capacity to create these but complete
recurrence you know right so does that
make sense I mean it doesn't make sense
but yeah and just confirming I would
make a subtle question but I would put a
subtle question around the the the
recognition we don't need to go down
this but the recognition that the
witness is not the nothingness because
uranus the witnesses subtle experience
the come from the prepared the perpetual
come from is nothingness or something
like that right but the it doesn't maybe
it does for different people i'm not
sure but that's sort of that collapse of
the witness always is it simultaneously
for me that a brightening of experience
itself so that content and everything
are just very simultaneous a knowledge
and the known are simultaneous and it
and so that there isn't really a
separation between the nothingness and
everything else too because they have
the quality of being yeah nothing the
same time so it's like it's not just
witness dissolves and then nothingness
can be highlighted but it feels like it
becomes very like
non dual simultaneously but even there
even there the nothing this can be
highlighted in the way that it's like
hmm what do I really want to say anyway
going back to what I've already said so
we don't need to go down there no no
you're moving it along because your debt
so that I'm just the first thing we
talked about inference I'm confirming
that you've moving into this long Buddha
Scholastica rate so this is this now
we're moving again and so one of the
things you're talking about now and then
we'll move again but I'm going slow for
our viewing audience and then when we
get so we don't need of us knows what
we're talking about then that'll be no
right yeah all right so you're right so
now there's something unsatisfactory
about inferring the opposite side of the
dualistic equation right this is what I
hear you saying so now I infer that
everything is object so what's I'm
inferring to is the other thing that can
never be seen now it can't be a subject
because the subject is also an object in
the awareness of this inferred thing so
now I have really screwed up right I
know to put sack I don't have to put on
the other side of the debt horizon where
I'm can only infer right now and I'm
going to make I have to make two moves
here so okay okay one of the things that
I've tried to do in my work is create
words that are placeholders for this
effect okay and the words I use is in
that line everything on one side of the
line is a perspective and then but
behind that line is a view right yeah
but those two things should not be seen
as they're not opposites like that's why
say subjects over here and objects over
there over there because that makes this
improper relationship right so now
you're going to ask me well how are they
related and we need to create a new
language to really understand how
they're related so so that's one thing
the other thing is this is what a little
bit around the same thing is if you
think of all the things you're talking
about now instead of in dualistic pairs
as if everything comes as a figure
aground you were talking about context
so the ground is the context and the
figure is that which is in context so
now we're not even seeing them as
simplistic dualistic pairs right but you
are aware that they're relativized their
relationship our relative eyes by this
figure ground quality right so now we
can say well can we would it now when I
look at what is figure grounding you
know then if you my experiences is if
you look at it carefully and look at it
is not witnessing it if you know what I
mean it is not an effortless activity it
is what the fundamental activity like
your eyes seeing seems effortless but
it's not actually effortless like if you
had absolutely no energy in your body
would not see and yet your eyes can only
see in a certain way they only see
certain colors and then ok so the figure
ground move is the first effort of the
kind of mind we have now ok so so
um I had this long taco Suzanne cooker
idea about this I said cuz she does this
she does this thing at the end of her
workshop her advanced work shot while
her workshop when she takes a piece of
paper and fold it in half and then cut
the heart out of it right I could do it
here I do I have a scissors oh come on
please anyway she cut the heart out of
it and then she says she asked the
people well what do we have here and
people's you know so i can only cut a
hole because you a whole bras this is
and actually this is probably more like
what i have in my heart center chakra
then kind of actual heart so i will just
go with it okay okay so it's a very
beautiful shape that you actually pretty
nice you know yeah i think it's better
this way is it better it's a little
nicer this way no I like today okay
alright so she says what do I have here
she says I have the heart the figure
rate and then I have its antithesis that
that no heart that inform emptiness but
I also have the ground the context right
okay so this is to her everything that
is able to happen in so I say but what
if that's just a temporary evolutionary
aspect of mind she's and it doesn't have
to be like that so she says she's really
cool she says she throws the
construction paper at me she says will
show me then I so I say what if it's
more like this and and I really wished I
could have done a really neat origami
but that things get folded I love it
double combat so so that's that's a
certain experience right we're in this
experience the object world seems to
be in front of and held by the witness
or something right or are the subject is
conventional ordinary experience but you
see nothing's broken and then I have a
non-ordinary experience the thing tends
to flip around at all all of a sudden
like happened to Alfred star heart his
his feeling Center was out in the world
so though you have a nature mysticism
the world is all the effect it doesn't
seem like it's inside of you anymore
it's out there and so that's just
reconfiguration yeah nothing gets broken
and so this is what I say is the form of
you know the next version of mind and so
when I hear you talking that's what I
hear you saying like you're not you're
trying to say well we have this this
result but things aren't really broken
and they're not really do list 'ok and I
hear you softly seeing something more
like this and then I can change it in in
the in the web is never broken but it
keeps getting reconfigured and reshaped
and and and so for me the homeless is
never it's more complex but it's also
like simpler like the wholeness is never
lost but it's never fixed in any way
there's no there's no there's no there's
no paradigm or meta view or finality
anywhere yeah there's a med of you that
can arise as a particular configuration
of the whole and then it can move and do
something else and it can move and do
something else and you know we it it's
it's a way to understand so in life
still you know there's no place for the
witness if the witness appears then it's
a configuration of the whole right and
if the witness it's not theirs emptiness
over here and then there's the whole if
emptiness appears it's a it's a kind of
configuration of body mind spirit and
experience and that appears like whoa
I've inferred emptiness so so this is
actually very helpful for me because
part part of the doubt has been well is
this really different or is this the
same thing that the you know Suzanne
kakoi der will take her as an example is
saying you know like she includes all of
reality figure ground and context you
know for using those metaphors and and
I'm and is my real is the whole that I'm
talking about really different or more
whole than hers and so you're having the
same insight which is supportive at
least so it yeah I think that that we
you know language does not help us out
because for 2,000 years no it doesn't
help us out because at this mind right
well it's actually really big big part
of what I'm talking about here because
it really is this is a its am I only get
it through feeling i only get it through
feeling what I'm hearing and what people
are where people are coming from what
they're living and what they mean by it
and there there there and the season
also the values that go along with their
emphasis so it's mmm sometimes I have
clear thoughts about it sometimes I do
not and I you know the clearest thought
they have about it or come when I'm
alone which is simpler yeah let's just
have me in my mind to deal with bow then
when I'm in relationship like in this
moment with you it's like oh we I don't
know I don't know if what you're saying
is what I'm saying and I just have to
like ule forward they say
uh well that's why you have to go slow
because because we can't get distracted
by language like if you took a
transcript of this it would just seem
like you know something that that that
Dada role or sometimes got a data is
amor something so you want to be careful
that that we're trying to feel into next
the experience or the awareness of this
different way you know we could back up
because because I and this might be
helpful or not but you know before this
mind was born we only had this mind and
it was the mythic mine and everything
was all good so pretty yeah we just went
around and around and around everything
eternal recurrence you know spring
became summer and summer became spring
and winter and it just went her in in
and then somehow right around Plato's
time he the mine started to work
differently it was very subtle then and
he called it diuresis you can take and
diuresis main separation and he sought
thought of it as the thought of the gods
and he said no we can take this out this
eternal returns and we can see it as a
myth relative to something else he made
he made it not everything he made it an
object that was separated called that's
where the dialectic comes from the term
diuresis and so I think what we're
talking about is the same thing we don't
yet have the language and the community
but what is happening the ability to see
in these new ways is coming through us
not because we can talk ourselves into
it we actually have to work at creating
language that it expresses what just
seems to be happening and happening to
more and more people and so
yeah so that to me is seems to be what
this process is are we you know if you
take courses from someone who of a
certain lineage are we smarter than them
you know it just seems to be we see
their teaching in a different kind of
carried forward or something that hasn't
that that hasn't been possible before
which i think is cool and and and so are
we going to try to tie this back into
transcendence or well I feel like we
have in a sense okay I didn't didn't
because well there's a couple ways of
saying it like the folded origami the
last one you made that at in which
there's no cuts there's no there's just
configurations we could say that that's
a we might say that that's a
transcendence of the preceding version
of understanding cellphone world because
you can have experiences it can it can
it can configure itself to have
experiences which confirm the previous
world view the previous view an
experience of just sitting is is that
which doesn't move in a stable way for a
while I'm not being true and then but
then so but then it can fault and then
but then you can fall out of it but not
with the sense of losing it or falling
out of it but of just reconfiguring I
think that's the difference that
nothing's lost its just reconfigured so
in a way it's a transcendence but if we
look but there's another way of putting
it which i think is more it comes from
the newer that that that newer mind I
guess we'll call it the origami mind the
origami mind origami mind I like that
yeah okay let's use that the origami
mind which for me I
think emphasizes relationship because
even the aura gump or even though
origami mind only makes any sense at all
in relationship to what came before so
the origami mind doesn't hold itself as
the viene the view of any of you it's
the it's it's in constant flux even you
understand myself is in constant flux so
and that actually soaks for me my
experiences that actually soaks into all
experiences is the emphasis and there's
maybe there's actually something here
around its primacy in the heart area is
that the end feeling I like and feeling
is that the emphasis becomes on
relationship relationship between
anything any view any experience any
person it's like relationship actually
seems primary and essential to every
moment and the unfolding rather than
anything and that's in relation yeah so
they call it unfolding which is
interesting um and now the whole concept
of relationship is really become
enriching and it's become origami so
because in the fragmented world how
things can be separate but in
relationship needed a third term so how
could my mind and your mind be separate
but related we'd have to have you know
over mind or ground consciousness or
there was always this need for a third
term which would transcend the
individuality and then would make a
transcendent imminent one mini problem
with the origami model relationships are
folds to the interface of folds of in
all reality what reality is is not a
particular
you but the capacity to create views by
folds or interface so now because we all
have a separation we don't have to fill
it with something that makes two things
touch we have to worry about that right
so so this is part of getting into this
whole new mindset is to understand
that's what I like about insights that
seem valuable is that they solve a lot
of these other problems and so then we
can start to look at well what is a fold
what is a fold you know and so for me
that thing between view and perspective
is a fold right and not a duality or
figure ground or anything it's a fold
and and this becomes very process rule
because all realities that
transformation of folds and unfolding
and there's not one major trajectory of
folding or one major trajectory of
unfolding that's also a Content context
move so yeah I mean it's a nice it's a
nice metaphor to play with this other
view to make distinctions on what seems
unsatisfactory about the transcendent or
absolute argument although it can point
to experiences that are psychoactive
well and the other tricky part is that
people who embody that deeply are often
have special insight or capability which
makes it seem very true or useful or
worth worth listening to and that
they're that they have that they are
worth listening to in a very profound
way yeah I think I think that part of
that comes from in my experience is that
the conventional view so now we're back
talking to their language right the
conventional view is a limiting view and
there's something about the organism
that knows that and then there's the
organisms always trying to get more
freedom so if you go and you receive a
transmission and you get your view
switched around right not that all your
life you're worried that you're going to
die and then you actually see the truth
in the opposite that you're never going
to die then because you've your view has
become so much increased like view for
me is degrees of freedom that that
releases a lot of energy and become
psychoactive because for your whole life
you're in this pattern and the
thicknesses is the lack of freedom and
so it's my understanding or my guess
that it's the non ordinariness it's the
fact that we happen to be in one pattern
and it gets unlocked but if it were vice
versa you know I tell the story of
beings who've only are subtle energy
beings in bliss and then someone goes to
a guru who says oh you know if you eat
food and you have sex you have this
completely embodied experience and
people are like no that's just a myth
and stuff and then people start like
actually doing the practice and having
these experiences well they would think
that those were transcending because
what it would transcend is ordinary
experience and it would be equally
psychoactive because it's not what view
you've moved to its that your view
increased degrees of freedom and to me
whether you come from one to the other
is is not the point so uh yeah that's a
route that's a really fascinating
thought experiment that's remain jurist
um you see you see for example Christian
mystics having great success tin in the
East for the same reason because all
their lives they've been taught this
very organic somewhat naturalized
concept of spirituality and now they're
getting you know God in the second
person or God in the first person and
because that has opened their view that
it's very psychoactive and then you get
this cost cultural convert you know like
so um though that's that would be my
guess yeah yeah I'm trying not to fill
in the space we've run mostly to the end
of what I would know to talk about yeah
we did a good I think we did a good i
like how these things have yeah they
like script themselves in a way you know
what do you mean um
like you know when they're starting and
then they kind of know when they're come
around to some kind of I'm going like
this cuz it makes me think of making
pizza dough oh I know is not very
sophisticated metaphor but you go like
that and then you're making pizza dough
and then you go around and around and
then it's somebody you just know it's
it's ready to proof so yeah I actually
think that it comes down to an ethical
question like which understanding of
reality is most makes the most space and
deeply honors in a feeling way you know
and also in a hot in a humble way a
humble way yeah what you don't know and
um and how people show up even when they
don't show up as impressive and and even
when you show up interiorly as having
great confidence because I think that's
another experience to have I actually
recently I've been noticing how great
confidence great confidence is an
energetic that can be embodied and it's
actually I think it's another ethic that
it should be related we should we should
make the time we should justify our
great confidence by continually testing
what we know but it doesn't actually
require that I can sit in great
confidence I can sit in the energetic of
great confidence and speak and not doubt
myself whether it has anything and
without it having anything to do with
what i actually think or what I might
actually say which I actually think has
a quality that comes from and deeply
deep stabilization of transcendent type
or can come you know you speak the truth
you speak what reality is but I think
that's a I think that's a safe place and
I think it's actually harder to see in a
humbler place this origami mind it like
not not recognized yeah I think that
it's it's the confidence that's not
conditioned you know it's a great
confidence of the happy dog right it's
just it's if that's where the humility
comes into its yeah the great confidence
of the happy dog there's no gap there
you know it's just in process in the
present all the time so yeah yeah yeah
it matters to me but yeah yeah so I
think it's um I don't know I mean you
can you can accept tremendous dealt with
with great confidence you know wait like
I have no idea right I'm
completely confident about that you know
right so yeah that's the that's what I
think you know yes I it is that is what
I'm saying that is what I'm saying and
then
I don't know how to describe the next
move it feels like a Brit that or the
shift from the cut out heart to the
origami mind is like it only have this
is something real like if you know it
only happened for me because of
transmission I mean it was it only
happened to me cause I hung out with
Samuel bunder yeah I originally
originally Ted Strauss another waking
down teacher but then say say no bond
and it keeps happening I just keep
finding myself like sucked into this
what this this sensual brightening this
terrible it's terrifying it's like it's
not where I want to go every time it
happens but it feels true or this
sensual brightening of the radical
relationship and paradox akala T paradox
akala T of absolute and relative views
and then there's nowhere else to go and
I just feel like I'm in the heart of
reality and it's and it and it it feels
like I enter a hidden world it's a
hidden world and it's not it doesn't
have and it's dark and it's and it feels
like I'm looking out from reality but it
doesn't necessarily come with the
clarity and confidence of the absolute
stance station because it's all mixed in
there the my experiences the permission
is given to the to the to the confusions
and the folds and the perspectives of
the relative views to such a degree that
is freedom there's that that that they
that their full validity is given is
expressed I live their full validity
basically so confidence is one of many
things I can experience but it's
certainly not the it's not necessarily
the place to live all the time
yeah I think one of the mysteries that
I'm fascinated with and is that how we
can come to the new understanding in the
language of in the framework of what
we're leaving behind you know so that's
what you said you know we're using we're
using words from Buddha scholastics
we're using references to conventional
experience and yet we're pointed
something that we're saying is radically
not that and so you know it this happens
with all at all levels you know so so
when Einstein was doing his work he was
doing it in the math and language of
Newtonian physics you know how could you
be inside a framework and within that
build getting the outside you know and
other a lot of people talk about this
but so you have to respect the framework
that is is the launching pad for its own
self transformation but I think part of
that is that we are a living expression
of the carrying forward of things we
don't make it up it makes us up somehow
and that's why I think the humility
comes in um or else you know like how do
you know these things how does anybody
know these things I don't know
I don't know either but one thing I have
been thinking is that you we just get
used to there's just enough people that
start talking this way that we get used
to thinking that it's true yeah there's
a there there is a um everyone you know
more and more people move along in two
different ways of knowing and it's
faster now because we all share the the
framework that it's the more people can
share the same framework now so more
people can find each other moving
through it I guess you know I think it's
a mystery oh we should ask your horses
now that you know something think that
the whole figure-ground thing I did
learn from my horses because horses
apparently from working for my working
with them they because they they've
evolved to pay more attention to the
environment and not to the figure
because they're because of prey animals
yeah and so once i figured figured that
out then the way i worked with them was
different oh this is what they're seeing
this is what they're feeling and sensing
these patterns not that I'm over here
talking to them over there and I started
to understand that there were different
ways of interpreting space and time and
movement and that was a figure ground
thing and then that was part of my
looking at that mm-hmm mm-hmm cool
that's cool it's it's nice to get
external confirmation of new insights
like oh this is true because it works
better with my horses I'm actually more
successful with them relate to them on
the basis of this site in sight yeah you
know we're always as a culture we're
always waiting for the aliens to come
and tell us
like completely different ways of
looking at things but if we if we and
then when we we interface with animals
we're fascinating with trying to get to
the animals to do sign language or the
animals to say our words and you know
and then we say oh they're not so smart
they don't learn so well but we never
take on trying to learn their language
and their view because you know what
it's really really hard and so like
animals come really close especially
domesticated animals to our world and
the average person has almost 0 capacity
to move into the animals world and so
who really is you know except shamans
you know that's what they did so who
knows how many types of views in terms
of configuration of being we could we
could play with if we were curious about
trying to understand animals you know
who knows what's what that's like you
know mmm wells ha did you want to get
back to non-ordinary experiences no I
think we're good we're good for now ok
great I want I just want to say I'm I'm
having it is an interesting experiment
for me to see how my intention again for
this call was to have our conversation
in the context of neutral discovery and
Endicott and the kind of insight coming
from between us yeah and it's difficult
for me to and maybe there are degrees or
something maybe it's just but it's
difficult for me to to rest there
there's so much that I have to say or or
want to know that I often feel like I'm
sort of chunking ideas out here
bonding with your chunks and I'm
chunking I just back at you rather than
the mystery between us coming up with
new ideas not knowing where we're going
to go before we get there I mean even
now that's doing it you know well i
think that there's there's I think we're
building that capacity you know I I
think that and I think it's pretty fast
like a lot of times i would have a
conversation like this with someone and
we would have been horribly stuck
arguing about the relative in the
absolute realms because it would become
clear that we didn't have the same
understanding or fluidity with those
terms and so my experience of what we're
doing is we're moving until we get to
that point right where there's a fold
right right so that that's a to keep
actually finished finishing yeah until
there's a fold that's the the new term
we made up so now we have a new word
that when we get you like but yeah it's
good because we're gonna say oh I think
this is a fold whereas before if we'd
say oh I think this is a relative or net
you know we'd be stuck in this thing
that didn't serve us very well so and
maybe one distinction a new distinction
to make then is that ok i don't really
like the idea of spectrum that maybe
types degrees spaces of inciting
collective inciting or something because
it's not hold there's not a whole
separation between our conversation but
there is a sense on my side that like I
had this intuition of a fold that I
wanted us to go to huh and we bent there
so it wasn't a total surprise it really
wasn't answered two questions that I've
had um right which would be different
than like hold on I think there's an
eagle on my lawn
huh oh no just a goose it came down
funny on the grass so it looked like it
was attacking something and that's it
yeah yeah sorry sorry ya know that this
was the other point that was the other
point that was like um because right
this is the other point that's like went
to a fold sort of knew where we were
going I wanted to get there but when we
were in the beginning with all the
language I knew that those are like
language traps all over the place there
and it didn't matter to me so much there
was degree to which it didn't matter to
me so much that we were getting our
language perfect or that I knew with
confidence that you were saying exactly
the same thing that I was with all those
terms around her like that absolute but
that there was a feeling between us of
going somewhere of the feeling of
movement more important to me just
because the conversation was better
because the resonance feels better but
also because it feels to me like in the
movement the questions get answered or
yeah or addressed at least rather than
getting stuck in that in the intensely
conceptual like right we weren't trying
to be conceptual we're trying to make
sure that our language could help us
rather than get us stuck and and like
that's why i said on what I knew we were
both and I pointed out we were both
trying to let the feeling of the
experience being be pointed to by
language and not just playing a language
game because that can that can have
outfield we did that but I yeah I think
that but this is a good foundation
because now we have this word fold it's
all sony how language works because that
word now is packed with meaning and it's
not a fancy word but it's a very
sophisticated
right now you know because it means none
of that relativism and absolutism and
transcendence and none of that dualistic
but doesn't mean the non-dual because we
know the non-dual is also the flip side
and all of that now we can talk about
from the origami mind I mean calling it
an origami mind maybe a problem with
this it's kind of sounds nice and then
like what was really convenient for me
is at one point I had to say now going
back into conventional Buddhism you know
somebody talking we're not making the
distinctions of their ground in mind
we're talking about this sector here and
then we know when we can ask each other
to drop in the conversation from this
more what call more sophisticated view
that we're just really feeling into its
implications the insights that can come
from that now and and i think the ease
in which it happened makes a false sense
of how you know the ease in which happen
between us i think is not indicative of
how much territory has been covered is
not indicative another meaning we move
we went through a lot of territory
easily yeah i would say so in my
experience with yeah true see this is
the problem with this work because you
use a word in it and then all the
problems with the stupid word right jump
out at you but we can trust each other
that we put yeah nadia problems aside
right right um I
so one direction I was inspired to go
from what you just said was origami mind
you know we've been talking for so maybe
this is just be a seed I don't really
yeah how far will get exactly but a
friend of mine oh it was it was Mark
Jerusalem he sent me the paper where you
outline view it wasn't your 2,000
pick-six paper it was like a shorter
paper yeah I tried to make a popular
version right good job well that's
interesting that you tried to make a
popular version and now you're using the
word origami mind because he was he was
saying that your expression of view or a
different structure or something came
across as a little bit state II like
state yeah oh yeah I want to make the
distinction that that or at least raised
the question that when I'm talking about
this new way there is a mind that can
understand it but okay ooh this is good
so I'm not talking cognitive I'm not
primarily talking about cognitive
structure I'm actually talking about a
contemplative realization a stable
embodied contemplative realization that
has all the qualities that has all the
qualities that defined other
contemporary realizations and it has a
cognitive component it has a it has it
has a cognitive component or aspect
which can understand itself this
realization from this from this viewer
perspective or this origami mind that
you're talking about and but it's not
primarily cognitive it's just that it
has a cognitive flower petal and that
cognitive flower or pedal is what I
think when you talk about post
dialectics post dialectical mind so it's
if there's this curious relationship
between the realization and mine and
weather and the cognitive capabilities
and cognitive patterns and and whether
that's opposed dialectic or not and all
that kind of thing so and it does feel
like the lines between the cognition and
the contemplative realization are sort
of blurred because I'm not just defining
mind as the thoughts and images and
words that occur in awareness I'm
talking about the process of
understanding and relating to and
resonating with and interfacing with
everything so even what cognition is is
a much deeper process it's not just
about thoughts and words and images it's
also about feelings it's also about
intuitions it's also just about this
very subtle sense of relationship each
those things all give rise to new
understandings and new ways and new
insights and so all of that is cognition
it's not in its and it's coming from
this whole place this always whole place
anyway moving and in a way a sense in a
sense then everything becomes cognition
in the sense of giving rise to new
understanding because as the origami
folds into new configurations new
learning occurs automatically so it's
it's like the world process itself has
lived through here is cognition it's
learning it's learning all the time so
even the boundaries between cognition
affect or cognition and and realization
they're starting to break down or blur
something like that yeah I mean we could
talk about this maybe we can just leave
this in and think of talking about
origami mind from the start next time
you know like get some feelings into
what what that is now that we
hypothesized this new thing
and we hold it lightly we know that that
we're building a perspectival world out
of an implicit view that is arisen and
is unfolding into the first spectacle
world we can drive ourselves crazy and
say well we're actually not origami mine
because if we can see origami mind we
absolutely must be something else but
right now we're just gonna talk about
origami mind and infer the other thing
you see this is to me why their self
system is generative because it's always
moving more stuff into the explicit
world that we can talk about and share
and the implicit world which is shared
right but not share a bowl so so you and
I share a common root at the source but
then as individuals we can't exchange it
because it's shared there but then
that's a whole nother thing but so maybe
we can just talk about that in its
relationship to you know there's other
distinctions to be made in terms of mind
vs comfortable did you call a
contemplative realization of the
realization yeah and states you know
States I what I talk about view at the
it's very hard for me to say what I
think view is but the most accurate
thing I can say is it's a verb not a
noun and it's degrees of freedom right
so
yeah and so that's that we can maybe we
could just stop there and look at maybe
those two terms next times origami mind
and in view and see where that goes or
not we might have a clean by have
something else that might be so passe
yeah well you know it's into that den
silly me one never knows